Abortion Collection
Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College
Abortion collection
1936-2005
MS 428
7 boxes (3.25 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
Primarily printed materials, plus legislative records, memorabilia, and audiovisual materials documenting the efforts of both the pro-life and pro-choice movements. The Legal status section documents specific court cases, with an emphasis on the Roe v. Wade case (1973). Organizations represented include the National Abortion Rights Action League (NARAL) and the Women's National Abortion Action Coalition (WONAAC).
The Abortion Collection is comprised of mostly published materials organized in six series: General, Legal status, Organizations, Countries, States and Opposition. Articles, pamphlets, newsletters, books, newspaper clippings, legislative records, memorabilia, and audiovisual materials document the efforts of both the pro-life and pro-choice movements from the 1930s to the present, although the bulk of the collection dates from the 1970s. The Legal status series documents specific court cases, with an emphasis on the Roe v. Wade case (1973), and includes court transcripts and audiotapes from the Supreme Court hearing. Organizations represented include the National Abortion Rights Action League (NARAL) and the Women's National Abortion Action Coalition (WONAAC). There are also clippings and newsletters on abortion-related issues in countries other than the United States. The Opposition series includes memorabilia, printed material, books and videotapes related to the anti-abortion rights movement.
This collection is organized into five series:
I. General
II. Law and Legislation
III. Organizations
IV. Countries
V. Opposition
Oversize Materials
The Papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection.
Periodic additions to collection are expected. Recent additions may not be reflected in the finding aid.
Original audiovisual recordings have been transferred to digital format for research use.
Materials in this subject collection were either purchased or given to the Sophia Smith Collection by various donors.
National Abortion Rights Action League--History; Women's National Abortion Action Coalition--History; Roe, Jane, 1947---Trials, litigation, etc.; Pro-choice movement--United States--History--Sources; Pro-life movement--United States--History--Sources; Abortion--History--Sources; Abortion--Moral and ethical aspects--United States; Abortion--Law and legislation--History--Sources; Abortion--Political aspects--United States
Related materials can be found elsewhere in the Sophia Smith Collection in the Records of the Abortion Rights Fund of Western Massachusetts, Catholics for Choice, National Network of Abortion Funds, Reproductive Rights National Network, SisterSong Women of Color Reproductive Justice Collective, Voters for Choice, Planned Parenthood Federation of America, Planned Parenthood League of Massachusetts, ProChoice Resource Center, and many others.
Note: For poster and other memorabilia from the March for Women's Lives, 26 Apr 2004, see the Miscellaneous Memorabilia Collection. For articles on that event, see the Health Collection.
- SERIES I. GENERAL
  - Abortion, Spontaneous and Induced: Medical and Social Aspects by Frederick Taussig, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Abortion Surveillance: annual summary, Center for Disease Control, 1973-75 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Abortion Trends newsletter, 1975-78 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Bibliographies
    - General, 1971-95, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Abortion Bibliography for 1970 compiled by Mary K. Floyd, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Buttons, cartoons, calendars, stickers, and miscellaneous memorabilia, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Clippings, 1964-77, undated (Box 1, Folder 7-8)
  - Demonstrations, 1972-75, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Doctors and medical students, 1973-95, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Documentary film trilogy, "From the Back Alleys to the Supreme Court and Beyond": marketing, publicity, and resource guide, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Fact Sheets, 1968-95, undated (Box 1, Folder 12-13)
  - International Inventory of Information on Induced Abortion, by Emily Campbell Moore-Cavar, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Methods
    - General, 1967-73, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Feminist self-help abortion, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Pamphlets and position papers
    - (Pre Roe v. Wade) 1964-72 (Box 2, Folder 4-5)
    - 1973-99, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Personal testimonies, 1974, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Psychiatric implications, 1966, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Religious opinions, 1970-82, undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Women of color, 1993, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
- SERIES II. LAW AND LEGISLATION
  - General, 1969-79, undated (Box 2, Folder 11-12)
  - Constitutional Aspects of the Right to Limit Childbearing: A Report of the U.S. Commission on Civil Rights, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - H earings Before the Subcommittee on Constitutional Amendments of the Committee on the Judiciary, United States Senate: Abortion Part 1; S.J. Res. 119 and S.J. Res. 130, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Massachusetts v. Brunelle: briefs, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 3-4)
  - Supreme Court oral arguments (on cassette) and transcripts, 1973, undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
- SERIES III. ORGANIZATIONS
  - Abortion Access Project: Increasing Access to Abortion Services organizing kit, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Abortion Law Reform Association, London, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Abortion Rights Coalition, Philadelphia, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - A.R.M. (Abortion Rights Movement of Women's Liberation), Washington, DC, 1979, undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Association for the Study of Abortion, 1966-76, undated (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Boston Women's Abortion Coalition, 1971-73, undated (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Catholics for a Free Choice, 1984-87, undated (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Commission of Population Growth and the American Future, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Committee for Abortion Rights and Against Sterilization Abuse (CARASA), 1979 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Concerned Citizens for Choice on Abortion (CCCA), 1981 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Feminist Organization for Communication, Action and Service (FOCAS), 1971, undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Gay Women for Abortion Law Repeal, Cambridge, MA, undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Massachusetts Organization to Repeal Abortion Laws (MORAL), 1970-73, undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - National Abortion Rights Action League/National Association for the Repeal of Abortion Laws (NARAL) (Box 4)
    - General, 1971-80, undated (Box 4, Folder 5-6)
    - Newsletter, 1976-82 (Box 4, Folder 7-10)
  - National Network of Abortion Funds and miscellaneous local funds, 1995, undated (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - National Organization for Women (NOW), 1969-98, undated (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - New Yorkers for Abortion Law Repeal, 1969 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Religious Coalition for Abortion Rights (RCAR)/Religious Coalition for Reproductive Choice, 1978-96, undated (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Society for Humane Abortion, Inc., 1964-73, undated (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Western Massachusetts Coalition for Reproductive Freedom, undated (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Women's National Abortion Action Campaign/Coalition (WONAAC), 1971- (Box 4, Folder 17-18)
  - Zero Population Growth: newsletter, National Reporter, Abortion issue, Aug 1970 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Miscellaneous, 1993-97, undated (Box 4, Folder 20)
- SERIES IV. COUNTRIES
  - "Capacity Building for Advocacy on Expanding Abortion Policy and Access: Sharing National Experiences Between Countries from Diverse Regions," Phase 1: first international meeting of NGOs organized by The Women's Health Project, Johannesburg, South Africa, (aka The Johannesburg Initiative): information packet for participants, circa 1999 (Box 5, Folder 1-2)
  - Clippings, 1970-79 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Sweden, 1964, 1972 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - United States
    - General, 1977-79, undated (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - A-Z, 1974-79, undated (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - California, 1967-79, undated (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Connecticut, 1979, undated (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Massachusetts, 1970-77, undated (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Minnesota, 1978 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - New York, 1970-78, undated (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Clippings (Box 5)
      - General, 1970-72, undated (Box 5, Folder 12)
      - Massachusetts, 1970-72, undated (Box 5, Folder 13)
      - New York, 1970-72, undated (Box 5, Folder 14)
- SERIES V. OPPOSITION
  - General, 1971-96, undated (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Black Americans for Life, 1994-95, undated (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Books
    - Alcorn, Randy. Pro Life Answers to Pro Choice Arguments, 1992 (Box 6)
    - Brennan, William. The Abortion Holocaust: Today's Final Solution, 1983 (Box 6)
    - Crutcher, Mark, Lime 5: Exploited by Choice, 1996 (Box 6)
    - Sweet, Gail Grenier, ed., Pro-Life Feminism, 1985 (Box 6)
    - Wilkie, Dr. and Mrs. J.C. Abortion Questions and Answers, 1991 (Box 6)
  - Videotapes--VCR
    - A Doctor Explains the Abortion Procedure, Dr. Noreen Johnson, 1994 (Box 6)
    - Meet the Abortion Providers, Pro-Life Action League, 1989 (Box 6)
    - Project Truth, Project Truth, Inc., undated (Box 6)
    - The Right Choice, Roman Archdiocese of Los Angeles, CA, 1993 (Box 6)
    - The Silent Scream, American Portrait Films International, 1984 (Box 6)
    - A Window to the Womb, Sound Wave Images, 1991 (Box 6)
- OVERSIZE MATERIALS
  - SERIES I. GENERAL: bumper stickers; sash from Pro-Choice Rally on the Mall, 5 Apr 1992; "Herstory of Abortion" by Colleen Wilson from unidentified publication, circa 1970 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - SERIES III. ORGANIZATIONS: Basic Quality of Live Issues, NARAL-Americans for Democratic Action Voting Chart for U.S. Senate, circa 1975; WONAAC Newsletter, Mar 1972, 1 Apr 1972, 29 Jun 1972 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - SERIES V. OPPOSITION: bumper stickers (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Posters, "Keep Abortion Legal" National Organization for Women, circa 1998; "The World's Abortion Laws 2005," Center for Reproductive Rights, 2005 (Map-case Flat File)